JUAN C. CONTRERAS

jcontrmo@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/juancontrmo/

Certified professional Developer (Oracle Forms - PLSQL - SQL) and Database administrator, in addition to Oracle Data Integrator (ODI) support experience helping customers to solve issues related to ELT mappings , performance, bug documentation, patching, testing, and ELT development. Skilled problem identifier and troubleshooter in a range of IT environments with certified knowledge of Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI); Bilingual English-Spanish, US citizen with employment history verified through an external company, see www.hireright.com.

Objective

Looking for challenging Database Developer positions according to my knowledge and experience (SQL + Data Modeling + PL/SQL + ELT + Database Administration).

Summary of Skills

Oracle PLSQL Developer, Oracle Forms, Bash Shell, O	Beginner Level: Oracle APEX, , Oracle Cloud, Python, GIT, OEM, GoldenGate
---	---

Education

Universidad Antonio Nariño – BS – Systems EngineeringBogota, D.C

1998

Certifications

- Oracle PL/SQL Certified Associate
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure Foundations
- Oracle Database Administrator
- Oracle Forms Developer

Technical videos:

YouTube channel <u>"JC Contreras – Just a curious Tech Guy"</u>
 Media channel with videos for Database Developers

<u>Video #1: Data Integration example between Oracle and SQL Server Video #2: Connecting Oracle SQLDeveloper to OCI & AWS (Part I)</u>
Video #3: Connecting Oracle SQLDeveloper to OCI & AWS (Part II)

Languages:

- English Advance Proficiency
- Spanish Native

Resume Spanish translation: https://jcontrmo.github.io/HojaVida/

Professional Experience

ORACLE – Senior Technical Support Engineer Orlando USA, FL Oct 21,2015 – Jul 15,2020

- Troubleshooting simple to complex Oracle data integrator issues for top account customers under SLAs predefined
- ODI upgrades from 11g to 12c versions for internal testing
- English-Spanish translator through phone calls and web conference to help Engineers Colleagues to provide support in ODI related issues.
- Configuration and design of virtual environments (database, OS, ODI agents) on Linux and Windows platforms to reproduce and solve ODI technical issues.
- ODI Topology Configuration to handle data integration connectivity with several source & target technologies
- Tuning of ODI developments, Memory, IO checking to provide best practices to improve ODI performance
- Documentation of solved issues to be published on my Oracle Support site
- Code review (PLSQL, Bash shell) to troubleshoot ODI issues
- Load data into Oracle tables using SQL Loader
- Verification of Database, OS System, WebLogic logs and Network to troubleshoot ODI issues
- ODI Source-target mapping among different technologies

<u>INDRA</u> – Database Administrator Bogota, D.C. July 9,2012 – Jan 31,2014

- Installed, configured, and managed Oracle 10g, 11g on windows and Linux platform.
- Interacted with the Technical Design team and contributed in impact analysis and creation of the technical specifications.
- Manage Database administration assignments in SQL Server environments
- Worked on Oracle databases and MSSQL, this included backup, restoration, and quality control
 applications.
- Developed windows scripts, shell scripts, PL/SQL programming for automation of database administration tasks
- Detailed review of Oracle Forms and PL/SQL code on customers to troubleshoot performance issues as part of the customer's software design.
- Developed and created a definition of backup strategies for RMAN and EXPDP.
- Created database structures for developer and client needs on QA and production environments.
- Applied security patches on Oracle databases.
- Involved in session management and monitoring the critical wait events, blocking sessions in the databases (Oracle and MSSQL).
- Worked on Migration of Oracle 11g Databases from Windows to Linux on Production environment

<u>EUD</u> – IT Certification Trainer Bogota, D.C. July 2011 – July 2012

- Training IT students in Database Administration, PL/SQL and Oracle Forms programming by using official Oracle documentation in order to help them to achieve Oracle Certifications.
- Installed databases and OS in classroom environments
- Provided recommendations to real issues happening on students' jobs related to PLSQL coding and Oracle Forms design according to best practices

<u>SYNAPSIS (TIVIT)</u> - Oracle Database Administrator Bogota, D.C May 5, 2010 – Dec 31, 2011

- Managed Oracle RMAN backups and tuning oracle sentences.
- Provided support for Oracle Data Guard administration
- Oracle database and MSSQL backups and recovery.
- Added more new features to existing analysis software tools.
- Created structural changes to the Oracle databases using DDL statements.
- Worked on Oracle configuration, third party backup software and backup testing.
- Supported DBA Junior SQL Server 2008 on replication scenario with log shipping.
- Made corrections of inefficient high load SQL statements, suboptimal use of Oracle database, undersized memory structures, concurrency issues, database configuration, and locking issues.
- Created Bash Shell scripts to invoke SQL Scripts and scheduled them using OS crontab
- Developed Complex PL/SQL Code, Stored Procedures, Functions, Packages and Triggers which uses collections as part of temporary developments assignments
- Applied analysis, data collection techniques, database normalization, entity relation modeling in SDLC from analysis, design, development, testing, implementation, and maintenance
- Reports generation based on multiple tables and subqueries by using ANSI SQL and T-SQL
- Involved in data loading using SQL Loader to load data from flat files
- Worked closely with clients to clarify development specifications

<u>Telefónica (Movistar)</u> – IT Database Professional – Bogotá, DC Nov 3, 2009 – Apr 1, 2010

- Utilize Oracle diagnostic tools like Explain Plan, SQL Trace, TKPROF and AWR to analyze timing and execution for database tuning
- Created and modified existing Unix scripts for Oracle 10g
- Managed Standard Audit trail, audit parameters
- Used triggers to record additional customized Audit information
- Worked with the development team for database object creation, query tuning and regular database related issues.
- Oracle database installation, patch installation, configuration, and maintenance.
- Tune the SQL queries by creating proper index, using hints, and changing database parameters
- Involved in development of application functions, triggers, PL/SQL and packages
- 24 x 7 database on call support according to shift rotation schedule

ORATECH LTDA

Aug 19, 2008 - Jul 22, 2009 Position: Infrastructure Consultant

- Managed the Oracle database (RAC-Standby-ASM).
- Acted as a consultant for software development tools, PL / SQL-forms-reports.
- Trained clients in Oracle database administration.
- Supported DBA clients (Falabella, Colombian Army, Thomas Express, Movistar).
- Visited clients on business sites, provided quotes configuration and created systems reports for clients and management.

SBD LTDA

October 2007 - August 2008

Position: Oracle Database Administrator

- Created users and privileges according with their responsibilities
- Configuring backup and restore procedures with RMAN scripts
- Tuned Oracle Sentences
- Developed scripts with PL / SQL and Shell scripting on Unix environments for DBA automated tasks
- Created and interpreting statspack reports
- Supported on call 24/7 DBA.

GEOSPATIAL

April 2007 - October 2007

Position: Development Leader Database

- Managed the Oracle development team on activities related with PL / SQL and Oracle Forms-Reports programming.
- Geodatabase Modeling, Use Case Specification
- Analyzed and design solutions according to the client requirements using RUP methodology
- Meeting clients face to face and on site to ascertain requirements.
- Producing and updating relevant documentation.

INFORMATICA SIGLO 21

November 2005 - March 2007 Position: Consulting Engineer

- Oracle10g Programming (Forms Builder, Reports Builder, PL / SQL)
- Development of New Buildings module and ranking contractors in Gas Natural ESP
- Application Maintenance NGV (Natural Gas Vehicle), IVM (Integrated Management of Sales), SAT
- Analyzed user requirements with UML methodology
- Design and Implementation of Business Applications using the Oracle Relational Database Management System (RDBMS).

SOFTMANAGEMENT

August 2003 - September 2005 Position: Senior Programmer

- Developed Complex database objects like Stored Procedures, Functions, Packages and Triggers using SQL and PL/SQL.
- Data analysis and generation of scripts for running reports
- Data analysis and generation of scripts for modification of information
- Change displays and programs Front-End, according to new requirements of the business.
- Programming Oracle (Forms 6i, PL / SQL and Reports), Procedures, Packages and Functions
- Involved in the support, maintenance, and development of the financial system
- Defining and generating screen formats and report designs using Oracle Forms and Oracle Reports
- Developed in accordance with policies regarding secure coding & standards
- Carrying out design, construction, review, and defect analysis activities.

• Developed using Oracle (Forms 6i, PL / SQL and Reports) in accordance with agreed design with consideration for usability, software quality and future maintenance

AVANZIT TECNOLOGÍA (new name Ezentis)

June 2000 - February 2002 Position: Oracle Developer

- Analysis and Design of security database modules
- Administration of databases in development and testing environment
- Project coordination SIGART for public sector telecommunication company
- Training for application users

SYNERSIS S.A.S

September 1999 - June 2000 Position: Oracle Developer

- Analysis, design and programming of the human resources Information System
- Oracle Development using (Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5, SQLPLUS).
- Testing on QA environments for new software
- Defining and generating screen formats and report designs.
- Produced and updatied relevant documentation for new developments.
- Develop software in accordance with agreed design with consideration for usability, software quality and future maintenance.

SOFTBOLIVAR - SEGUROS BOLIVAR

April 1998 – June 1999 Position: Oracle Developer

- Design and development of programs and reports for capitalization products
- Oracle Development using Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5, SQLPLUS

PERSONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

- **B**e able to adapt professionally and linguistically to support my family after moving from the country which I was born to the US 6 years ago.
- 5k runner in Orlando FL during two consecutive years
- Join the Catholic Christian community as an active member

JOB REFERENCES

Please check my LinkedIn connections, some of them know me very well.